<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[An exact] relation of the several engagements and actions of His Majesties fleet, under the command of His Highness Prince Rupert and of all circumstances concerning this summers expedition, anno 1673 / written by a person in command in the fleet.</title>
            <author>Person in command of the fleet.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38958</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7122</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12027722</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12027722</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52683</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38958)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52683)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 867:17s2008    miun a)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[An exact] relation of the several engagements and actions of His Majesties fleet, under the command of His Highness Prince Rupert and of all circumstances concerning this summers expedition, anno 1673 / written by a person in command in the fleet.</title>
                  <author>Person in command of the fleet.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J.B.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproductions of original in Bristol Public Library, Bristol, England (reel 867:17) and Folger Shakespeare Library (reel 2977:1).</note>
                  <note>Wing lists copies of 2 editions of this book under one number. The Folger copies of these 2 editions have been arbitrarily assigned Wing number E3696 and Wing number E3696a.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: first two words on t.p. cropped.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rupert, --  Prince, Count Palatine, 1619-1682.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Royal Navy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52683:1"/>
            <p>RELATION Of the Several ENGAGEMENTS AND ACTIONS OF HIS MAJESTIES FLEET, Under the Command of His Highneſs Prince Rupert: And of all Circumſtances concerning this Summers Expedition, <hi>Anno</hi> 1673.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by a Perſon in Command in the FLEET.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. B. Anno Domini.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:52683:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52683:2"/>
            <head>An Exact Relation, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>INCE my coming from Sea, I have Read the ſeveral Prints which have been publiſhed, and have alſo in daily conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation about Town obſerved the various Reports, and opinions of Men, every one diſcourſing as he ſtands affected, touching the Conduct and Behaviour of the ſeveral Squadrons of his Majeſties Fleet by Sea, during this Expedition: I perceive, that through the heat of Mens manifold Contradictions both in Court and City, the Story of the whole matter is told only as this and t'other Faction, or Affection would have it, by which means the Truth of things hath been hidden from His Majeſty; and is like to be from the Parliament and People of <hi>England,</hi> unleſs there ſtand forth ſome faithfull Relator. Therefore in all Loyalty to my King, and with a moſt affectionate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to His Service, that He and His Parliament may truly underſtand where the fault lies, that they, after ſo great an expence of Blood and Treaſure, have reaped no greater fruit of ſo grand an undertaking; I conceive it my Duty, having had the opportunity to be an Eye Witneſs of every Motion and Action from firſt to laſt, and being no way obliged to favour or disfavour any Party concerned therein, to take Pen in hand, and give this clear account of the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:52683:3"/>
            <p>But before I come to Matter of Fact, it will be very convenient to acquaint you with ſome Particulars, the knowledge whereof is abſolutely neceſſary to gain a right underſtanding of the Subject here related.</p>
            <p>After a continuation of the War this laſt Summer with the <hi>United Provinces</hi> had been Reſolved on by His Majeſty, the next thing to be thought on was the appointing a Commander in Chief over the Fleet that ſhould be ſent forth; and concerning the Perſon, though all Men judged the Employment of Courſe might continue in the Hands of His Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> as Lord High Admirall of <hi>England,</hi> yet upon weighty Reaſons of State, it was at length thought beſt for the good of this Kingdom, which is highly concerned in the ſafety of the Heir Apparent of the Crown, that at preſent His Royal Highneſs ſhould be excuſed from running any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hazard of his Perſon in ſo dangerous a Service; he having already too often Expoſed himſelf at Sea with high Courage and Reſolution; and therefore His Highneſs Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> being nominated, as the next fitteſt Perſon to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take that Command, His Majeſty was pleaſed to reſolve thereupon. And with this His Majeſties purpoſe there im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately enſued a marvelous Concurrence of the Peoples Affections in City and Countrey, (all over the Kingdom) as well in Regard of the Royal Stock from whence His Highneſs ſprang, as of His high Courage, Conduct, and long Experience in Affairs Military by Sea and Land, in this, and many other Nations; but yet more in reſpect of His tried Conſtancy to, and zeal for the <hi>Reformed Proteſtant Profeſsion of Religion,</hi> and all the Intereſts thereof, for the ſake whereof He and His Royal Family had long ſuffered the utmoſt extremity: The Senſe whereof was that which chiefly drew the Hearts of the People to rejoyce in His Majeſties Aſſignation of that moſt illuſtrious Prince; it being at ſuch a time when the Parliament had taken Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizanſe of the Confidence and Inſolence of the <hi>Popiſh Party;</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:52683:3"/>many of which being crept into places of Truſt and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, gave an univerſal jealouſie to the Kingdom, in ſomuch that His Majeſty and the Parliament ſaw it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, for the breaking of their Strength and Confidence, to <hi>put an Univerſal Teſt</hi> upon all men that held any publick Office or Imploy by Sea or Land, in order to the removing of all ſuch, as not ſubmitting thereto, ſhould be found <hi>Popiſhly affected.</hi> But yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this general Approbation and Applauſe of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in Chief, there were a Generation of Men of another mind, who having found all their Arts and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of diverting His Majeſty from this choice to be in vain, tack'd about to the <hi>old trick of State,</hi> of deviſing how underhand to take off the Chariot Wheels of the Princes Expedition, and to <hi>clap on dead weight to retard him;</hi> and ſo to handle the Matter among all ſorts of Navy and Sea-Officers, that partly defect of due preparation, furniture, and ſupplies might diſable Him, partly the ill timing of every Requiſite, and finally the ſtarting of Intereſts diſcontents and little Feids in the Fleet, might render the whole Enterprize of no more Effect than might juſt ſuit with their own Ends, and if poſſible, bring back the Prince with no more Victory than what might pleaſe them, and their Accomplices. In order hereunto, it is worth the while to conſider how pat things were laid and fell out; for, our Preparations were ſo delay'd, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> got their Fleet out before us; and after we were in part ready, it was towards the end of <hi>April</hi> before the Prince could get his Commiſſion, and Inſtruction to act by them; ſo that the <hi>Dutch</hi> having a Deſign to ſink <hi>Sinkers</hi> between the <hi>Middle Grounds,</hi> to ſpoil the going of our Ships out and into the River, were very near the effecting of it; and had done it, but that His Highneſs ſuſpecting it, with much induſtry got together as many of the 4th. and 5th. Rate Ships as he could, and ſome Fire-ſhips, with which he went quickly out, and defeated the Miſchief they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:52683:4"/>
            <p>Matters being carried thus tardily by Friends at home, the ſame ſpirit ſeem'd alſo to poſſeſs our Confederates on the Coaſt of <hi>France:</hi> ſo that there was the more urgent neceſſity for us to have doubled our diligence, and to have made all imaginable haſt, For, we had certain intelligence, that the <hi>French</hi> Fleet, being then at <hi>Breſt,</hi> would not ſtir from their own Coaſt, till they ſhould hear that Ours were got into the <hi>Channell;</hi> ſo that even then an <hi>ill Omen</hi> aroſe in our minds, that they, in time of Action, might fall ſhort of ſuch alacrity as becomes ſo grand an undertaking: Eſpecially ſeeing we had at the ſame time Intelligence alſo, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> were labouring night and day to augment their Fleet, and would grow ſtronger and ſtronger every day. It being therefore neceſſary we ſhould joyn the <hi>French</hi> with all ſpeed, His Highneſs reſolving thereon, gave a high proof of His Courage in all Attempts, to paſs in deſpight of the Enemy then Riding nigh the <hi>Gunfleet;</hi> and of his Prudence, in ſo cleanly paſſing with the Fleet againſt the Wind, through a paſſage of ſo great hazard as the <hi>Narrow;</hi> For which hazard, tothe endangering of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties whole Fleet, the Nation ows much tot he Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of thoſe delays, which gave the <hi>Dutch</hi> opportunity to reduce His Highneſs to the neceſſity of ſo paſſing, if he meant to unite with the <hi>French:</hi> Which brave Atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his ſtruck ſuch a terror into the Enemy, that they durſt not abide by it, but bore away to their own Coaſt, to ride ſecure upon their Guard within the Sands at <hi>Schonevelt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Gallant Action of His Highneſs deſerves ſo much the greater Eſtimation, ſeeing never any Prince went forth upon a War for the publick good, and the Honour of any Nation, under greater diſcouragements. For, ſome Perſons of high Truſt under His Majeſty had ſuch an Influence upon Affairs, that when they could no longer hinder the iſſuing forth of His Highneſs Commiſſion, they took care ſo to qualifie and Curtail it, that they left
<pb facs="tcp:52683:4"/>him not power to make ſo much a one Officer in the whole Fleet, unleſs he could upon requeſt obtain the favour ſo to do ſo that Perſons were put upon him for Sea-officers, from whom (for the moſt part) as he could have no particular aſſurance of affection to himſelf, ſo he was altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted, whether they had moſt Faith and Firmneſs to His Majeſty and the Kingdoms Service, or to the Intrigues and Service of their own <hi>particular Patrons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this account it was, That when the Prince had pitched upon Sir <hi>Robert Holmes</hi> for Imployment under him, as a Man of tried Valour, Fidelity, and Experience in Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fights, and one that his Highneſs could ſafely Confide in, being one that from his Youth had been Educated in his Flighneſs<hi>'s</hi> Family, it was ſo carried that he could by no means be admitted into any Command: and becauſe of ſome animoſity betwixt him and Sir <hi>Edward Spragg,</hi> that one point was made uſe of, as a pretence for the laying of him aſide, notwithſtanding the earneſt Endeavours of the Prince to have got his old Servant along with him; one whom he might ſurely have relied on. And to that end, his Highneſs had propounded ſuch ways and means to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile the matter, ſo as to make both of them uſeful to the publick Intereſt, and to ſatisfie the Reaſon of all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted Objectors, if they had had a mind to be ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>But it ſeems by what fell out afterwards, that they had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther work for Sir <hi>Edward Spragg</hi> to do beſides fighting by Sea; and therefore the ſacrificing of Sir <hi>Robert Holmes</hi> to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy, and the laying him aſide from the opportunity of pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the management of Sea-affairs, was a thing by them judged on divers accounts at this time abſolutely neceſſary to their ends; for they had determined (as appears) to ſend Sir <hi>Edward Spragg,</hi> though Vice-Admiral of the Blew Squadron, on a ſpecial Journey by Land to negotiate in the Court of <hi>France</hi> (who ſurely is the firſt Vice-Admiral that ever went out of <hi>England</hi> to the <hi>French,</hi> to learn how to Fight by Sea) where he was Graciouſly Received, Highly
<pb facs="tcp:52683:5"/>Careſſed, and thence Nobly Diſmiſſed (ſome ſay with a <hi>Jewel,</hi> &amp;c.) and all this ſo carried, that it was without the privity of <hi>Prince Rupert,</hi> who perhaps knows not to this minute, and no more then His Majeſty does, what buſineſs he tranſacted there.</p>
            <p>Nor was this all; for, to make ſure work yet further, it was as cautiouſly provided, that his Highneſs might not be crowded with too many Concerns; for, when His Majeſty in his Royal Wiſdom thought fit, to give him a Commiſſion to raiſe a <hi>Maritime Regiment,</hi> which was to have been paid out of the Eſtabliſhment of <hi>Ireland</hi> by my Lord <hi>Ranelagh,</hi> they preſently caſt about how to fruſtrate this Order of the Kings, and thereupon offered ſo ſpecious Reaſons for it to his Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> that he was thereby induced to divert His Majeſties pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in that matter. So there was an end of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</p>
            <p>And for the Chief Officers of his Highneſs's own Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, it muſt be remarked alſo, how he was accommodated <hi>(viz.)</hi> with Sir <hi>John Harman</hi> for his Vice-Admiral; which is not mentioned as if any fault could have been found with Sir <hi>John Harman,</hi> if he had then been the Sir <hi>John Harman</hi> he once was, (that is to ſay) the ſame Active man and Gallant Commander; but alas! he was Sick when he went aboard, and there tyed by the leg in his Cabin with the Gout, not able to ſtir either hand or foot. The appointed Reer-Admiral of the <hi>Blew</hi> was Capt. <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough,</hi> who being then abſent in the <hi>Streights,</hi> came not in till after the two firſt Engagements; which otherwiſe might have occaſioned ſome competition among the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Fleet for that Place: For, though he were a good Seaman, yet there were many others in the Fleet that were of better merit, and longer Service; and the offence that muſt have been given to others, had he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed it, was taken off by putting a Perſon of ſo great Quality as my Lord <hi>Oſſory</hi> into the Place. His Highneſſes
<pb facs="tcp:52683:5"/>own Reer-Admiral, was Sir <hi>John Chicheley,</hi> a Perſon of Honour and Quality, yet but of late a Seaman: which is not ſaid with intent of diminution, but only to give a clear account of things: For though a man may be of ever ſo much merit in other Qualifications, yet if he be put upon any Office or Employment, the leſs Experience he hath had therein, the leſs advantage he is like to bring to the Service.</p>
            <p>By theſe things it appears how the main Wheels were clogged, and how ſick the Officers muſt needs be, and how faint the hearts of the whole Fleet, to obſerve how they were dealt with upon ſo important an occaſion, as a War for the Intereſt and Honour of the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; eſpecially when they ſaw they wanted both Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Tools for the work, (that is to ſay) <hi>Seamen</hi> and <hi>Supplies.</hi> As for Seamen, <hi>it</hi> is to be noted, That though the Prince made it his Buſineſs to urge the getting of them betimes, Yet notwithſtanding all his ſollicitations, the Order for impreſſing of Seamen could not be got till it was very late, ſo that it was the Month of <hi>March</hi> before the Preſs began, though in the precedent year it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan as early as <hi>November.</hi> But though it was this year ſo late as <hi>March,</hi> yet even then, matters were ſo carried, that it was impoſſible for his Highneſs to be ſufficiently Mann'd, ſeeing the Preſs-warrants were of little effect, being Checkt by Protections which had before been granted to Thouſands of Sea-men &amp; Fiſher-men, and Water-men that would have made good Sea-men. Nevertheleſs, his Highneſs abating no whit of his Affection and Zeal for His Majeſty and the Nations Service, reſolved to break through all diſcouragements; and as ill accommodated as he was, ſeeing the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet were got out, braving it upon our Coaſt, did with all Expedition haſten forth to Sea; being fed at leaſt, and ſet forward with ſome empty promiſes, That Sea-men and Neceſſaries ſhould be ſent after him; which proved at length to be but a miſerable Slurr put upon
<pb facs="tcp:52683:6"/>ſo high a Commander: And all other things miſerably ſuited, when after it drew on to the Point of Action; as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the enſuing part of this Relation.</p>
            <p>For, on the 27th. day of <hi>May,</hi> which was the day before our firſt Engagement with the Enemy; when his Highneſs perceived they would not admit of a Fight in fair Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>room, but kept to their Advantage riding within the Sands at <hi>Schonevelt,</hi> He according to a reſolve of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of War (His Majeſty preſent) like a Magnanimous Prince, reſolved to Fight them in that very place, rather then permit them to wear away the Summer with longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays; which they ſeemed mainly to intend: which is the higheſt proof of Courage, the like Action having never been attempted in that ſtation before. So all the Sands having been ſounded ſome days before, and it having been concluded at a Councel of War held on Board the <hi>Royal Charles,</hi> to Attack the Enemy Riding there at Anchor in a Line between the <hi>Rand</hi> and the <hi>Stony Bank,</hi> his Highneſs on the 28th. day about 9 a Clock in the Morning Commanded the firing of a Gun, upon which we looſed our fore-top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſail, and Weighed, and Hoiſted the <hi>Union Flagg</hi> on the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Signal to Sail on towards the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. This was accordingly obeyed by a Squadron that was ordered out of the ſeveral Diviſions of the Fleet, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all of 35. Frigats, and 13. Fireſhips, who went with an eaſie Sayl, the Wind at <hi>S. S. W.</hi> In the mean while the Body of the <hi>French</hi> (all, except ſome who ſtragling got into our Diviſion, did indeed behave themſelves very gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantly) made little or no Sail, but kept in the Reer of us, though they ſaw the <hi>Hellander</hi> ſtretch it to the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Then the Prince petforth the <hi>Red Flagg</hi> on the Fore-topmaſt head; ſo all our Commanded Ships went a head, and by 12. a Clock at Noon Engaged the Enemies Van, Commanded by <hi>Tromp:</hi> The Prince himſelf alſo En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged two hours before the <hi>French;</hi> in which time we ſo preſſed <hi>Tromp,</hi> that he was forced to give way, and retire
<pb facs="tcp:52683:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>as far as the Sands would give him leave: Then the Count <hi>d'Eſtrees</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Squadron became at length Engaged with <hi>de Ruyter:</hi> which proſpered not ſo well; for, they bore him not down, but rather left him. And <hi>de Ruyter,</hi> not to be behind with them in kindneſs, quitted them, and came to his Highneſs; whoſe Squadron being too near the Shore, was for that Reaſon neceſſitated to ſtand the other way, to ſuch degree, that had it not been for fear of the Shoales, we had driven them into their Harbours, and given His Majeſty at that time a better account of them, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ill accommodations that we were under; more particularly in the <hi>Royal Charles,</hi> his Highneſs<hi>'s</hi> own Ship, which proved ſo Cranck-ſided, and fetch'd ſo much Water in at the Ports, that her lower Tire of Guns could not be made uſe of, though it was a very eaſie Gale that we had during this Engagement; the Iſſue whereof was, That the Enemy had many Men ſlain, many Ships diſabled, and ſome deſtroyed; Yea, and <hi>de Ruyter</hi> and <hi>Tromp</hi> muſt have been burnt by our Fireſhips, had they done their Duty. We ſaw two Ships ſunk. The <hi>French</hi> ſay they ſaw one burnt, two diſabled, and three run aſhoar. The Loſs on our ſide was very inconſiderable, two of our Ships being only diſabled, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Reſolution:</hi> very few Common Men were loſt, and only theſe Officers, Capt. <hi>Fowlis,</hi> Capt. <hi>Worden,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Finch.</hi> Colonel <hi>Hamilton</hi> had his Legg ſhot, of which returning home, he dyed at <hi>London.</hi> All the reſt that Engaged came off very bravely.</p>
            <p>Now from the time of this Action to the 4th. of <hi>June</hi> little was done, ſave the repairing of defects, and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Tackle, towards which we were all ill furniſhed as we were with all other Neceſſaries, not having ſo much as Needles and Thread ſufficient for the work, to the great Praiſe of our Providers be it ſpoken. And though his Highneſs had made it his Buſineſs Night and Day to get the promiſed Supplies of Sea-men aboard, and ſome had
<pb facs="tcp:52683:7"/>undertaken to do it, yet it came to no Effect. On the 3<hi>d.</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> which was the day before our <hi>Second Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> his Highneſs ſuſpecting the Enemy, that Riding on their own Coaſt they might be refitted and furniſhed with all things, the which benefit they knew (as the Wind ſtood) we could not have, and ſo would be Encouraged to come out again upon us, beſtirred himſelf exceedingly to get into a poſture fit to receive them: and not preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to truſt himſelf the ſecond time in the <hi>Royal Charles,</hi> he this day quitted her, and having opportunity of Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, went aboard the <hi>Royal Soveraign,</hi> where imagining the Enemy might Attack us that Night, he went not to Bed, but waited till Morning, <hi>June</hi> the 4th. when about 9 a Clock our Scouts gave the Sign, That the Enemy was a Weighing with freſh Sea-men and Proviſions, to take their advantage againſt us, as they very fairly had it; for then a ſtrange thing was done by Sir <hi>Edward Spragg,</hi> who, though he was told of the Enemy, and ſaw them himſelf, yet would needs loſe ſo much time as to come ſix Miles in his Boat, and bring his Reer Admiral my Lord of <hi>Oſſory</hi> along with him aboard the <hi>Soveraign,</hi> under a pretence of Buſineſs; the Conſequence whereof was, That the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my coming on with the advantage of a ſtiff Gale of Wind at <hi>N. E.</hi> The Blew Squadron Commanded by Sir <hi>Edward Spragg,</hi> by reaſon of his abſence, ſtood not away cloſe by the Wind to the Northward, as he had been Ordered to do, though his Highneſs with all poſſible ſpeed haſtened him back; who being got on Board, at length, after loſs of time, made Sayl to the Northward. This paſſage of Sir <hi>Edward Spragg</hi> being obſerved by Count <hi>d' Eſtrees,</hi> he thereupon took occaſion to lay by, and delay time; which point of behaviour we knew not what to think of, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſeaſon of Action, for that the <hi>Dutch</hi> were bearing down to us. And now more then ever we became ſenſible of the want of Sea men, not having enough to Weigh up our Anchors; ſo that to prevent a greater miſchief, his
<pb facs="tcp:52683:7"/>Highneſs was conſtrained to order the cutting off his own Cable, that we might be up with the Enemy. By this time <hi>Tromp</hi> with the Van became Engaged with <hi>Spragg,</hi> and <hi>de Ruyter</hi> with his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> who made a ſhew as if he would come very near us; but before he came within Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet ſhot, he ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng his Loof, and cloſed his Wind as much as he could, going off on a ſudden for good and all; and then cloſing with <hi>Tromp,</hi> their whole Fleet being bravely repulſed, they cautiouſly ſtood Pelting at us at a great diſtance, that they might be the nearer to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve of ſecurity within the Sands at <hi>Schonevelt</hi> upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. It was about 5 a Clock in the Afternoon that the Engagement began; and when they were reduced to Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, it ſo continu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d till 11 or 12 a Clock at Night, we all the while keeping our Ground, notwithſtanding their Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips; after which they Tack'd, ſtanding towards the Eaſt Southerly. (Then about two in the Morning we Tack'd alſo, and ſtood after them; but ſeeing no likelyhood of reaching them before they could get within the Sands, we thought not meet to follow them any further, and ſo Tack't again and ſtood for our own Coaſt. What Loſs they ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, we, by reaſon of their going off in ſuch a Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, cannot tell. On our ſide we loſt very few of our Men, and of our Commanders only Capt. <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> of the <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Sadlington</hi> of the <hi>Crown</hi> were killed; of the Foot Officers, Capt. <hi>Henſhaw,</hi> and Lieutenant <hi>Fitz Gerald;</hi> and Lieutenant <hi>Tuſton</hi> was Wounded? But for our Ships, as in the <hi>firſt Engagement,</hi> after we had ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently beaten the Enemy, we came off without the loſs of one man of War, or ſo much as one Ship touching the Ground, though that Fight was maintained in a dangerous place. So in this <hi>Second Engagement,</hi> wherein the Enemy came on with the advantage of the Wind, Freſh Men, and Proviſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> againſt us, we loſt never a Ship, and but few Men. For which His Majeſty and the Nation owes much, next under God, to his Highneſs, who at a
<pb facs="tcp:52683:8"/>time when non ſupplies, and want of Men, and of all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, would have ſtartled any man, gave ſuch ſignal Evidence of his Courage, Diligence and Prudence in the Conduct of the Fleet, as is Admirable to conſider in ſo great Diſcouragement and Diſorder as we were under, by reaſon of the prepoſterous behaviour and delays of ſome others.</p>
            <p>The next day, being <hi>June</hi> the 5th. and no Enemy in ſight, we had leiſure to conſider our Condition; and then from the whole Fleet came miſerable complaints to his Highneſs of want of Sea-men, and all manner of things in every Ship; though all things had been often written for, and promiſed they ſhould be ſent after us; the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders exclaiming they ſhould be thus expoſed, ſo as not to have convenient Supplies, but be in want of Powder, Shot, Water, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eer, and ſmall ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, Fiſhes, and what not; whereupon it being impoſſible to avoid a going home, to revictual and refit our ſelves preſently, we ſet Sayl for the <hi>Gun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et,</hi> and about 9 a Cloc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Night came to an Anchor there, and thence the following day made towards the <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oy of the Nore,</hi> where on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>June</hi> we Rode at Anchor, and on the 14th. his H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>London</hi> to give His Majeſty an Account how things ſtood, and to Preſs on a ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dy ſupplying of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll Neceſſaries for the Refitting of the Fleet out to Sea again.</p>
            <p>On the 21ſt. his Highneſs returned to the Fleet again, where, with indefatigable Induſtry, he ſet all things in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs, and made ſo quick diſpatch, that had not a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay intervened, about a deſign of ſending Soldiers to be Landed by us in <hi>Holland,</hi> we had been mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h ſooner out at Sea: but by their 6th. of <hi>July</hi> his Highneſs Weighed, and His Majeſty alſo in his Yacht, having a ſtrong Gale at <hi>S.W.</hi> and came to the <hi>Middle-ground,</hi> where humbly taking his leave of His Majeſty, he quickly got the Fleet through the <hi>Narrow,</hi> and on the 19th. of <hi>July</hi> ſtood with an eaſie
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52683:8"/>Sayl for the Coaſt of <hi>Zealand.</hi> The next day we diſcovered the Enemies Fleet at Anchor in the <hi>Schonevelt,</hi> bearing <hi>S.E.</hi> of us: On the 22d. in the Morning we ſtood to Sea, the Enemy no ſooner perceived it, but they ſtood after us, and the Wind Veering ſuddenly to the <hi>S. W.</hi> made them get the Wind of us, ſo that none of our Ships could wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them. And to wave an Engaging, for which when they ſaw us putting our ſelves in Order, they ſtood for their own Coaſt again, and we purſued our Reſolution of ſtanding along their Coaſt, which we did the 24th. look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ly</hi> to Anchor fair off of the <hi>Texel.</hi> So that on the 9th. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> we had the opportunity of taking one of the <hi>Dutch Eaſt India Ships,</hi> called the <hi>Papenburgh,</hi> making homewards. On the 10th. we had ſight again of the <hi>Holland Fleet</hi> ſtanding to the Northward, and bore down to them. Then his Highneſs Commanded the <hi>French</hi> a particular courſe, the Enemy being come three Leagues to Leeward of us; but here the <hi>French</hi> were plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to give us an early Taſt of their Temper: For, their Fleet lay by twice that Night, and made ſo little Sayl, that the Enemy had opportunity to ſtretch out a head of us. The firſt time that the French now faltered thus was about 11 a Clock at Night; which his Highneſs wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at, as contrary to Order, our whole Fleet was forced to lye by whileſt a Meſſenger was ſent on Board the Count <hi>d Eſtrees</hi> to know the Reaſon, and to Order him to make Sayl again. Nevertheleſs, after a little more Sayl made, he about one a Clock in the Morning laid his Sayles to the Maſt again; which gave a ſecond ſtop to our Fleet, while his Highneſs ſent a Meſſage by a ſecond Meſſenger to the ſame purpoſe. And by this means the <hi>Dutch,</hi> making all the Sayl they could, and the Wind Veering to the <hi>E.</hi> and <hi>E.</hi> by <hi>S.</hi> they got the advantage of the Wind of us, being cloſe by the Shore under <hi>Camperdown.</hi> About day-break we ſaw them about a League and half to Windward of us, the Wind being then at <hi>E. S. E.</hi> fair Weather: at which
<pb facs="tcp:52683:9"/>time both our Fleet and theirs were ſtanding to the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Upon this his highneſs ſtretch't it away till ſix in the Morning, being Monday the 11th. of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> The <hi>Dutch</hi> being then to Windward, began to bear down upon him: Whereupon his Highneſs thought fit to Tack, not having Room to the Eaſtward to Fight; by which Tack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fleet was brought into a very good Line and Order. The Wind now at <hi>S. E.</hi> his Highneſs prepared all things for a full and deciding Battel, putting abroad the Signal for our Fleet to Tack to the Southward; which they did. He had put the <hi>French</hi> in the Van, himſelf in the Middle, and Sir <hi>Edward Spragg</hi> in the Reer. Our Fleet being extended longer then the Enemies, and the Wind coming to the South, the <hi>French</hi> lay fair to get the Wind of them. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the Enemy bore down and Engaged us; <hi>de Ruyter</hi> undertook his Highneſs; <hi>Tromp</hi> provoked Sir <hi>Edward Spragg</hi> and his Blew Squadron, who laid his fore-top Sayl to the Maſt to ſtay for him, contrary to his Highneſs<hi>'s</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Orders, and his own Duty; while <hi>de Ruyeer</hi> and <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaert</hi> Vice Admiral of <hi>Zealand,</hi> both of them with all their Men of War and Fire-ſhips, came down upon his Highneſs his Red Squadron, except eight Men of War of the <hi>Zealand Squadron,</hi> whom <hi>Bankaert</hi> had ſent with three Fireſhips to fall upon the Reer of the <hi>French</hi> Squadron; where Monſieur <hi>de Martel,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Vice Admiral, being Cannon ſhot nearer to the Commanded party of <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> then any other Ship of his Diviſion, received Five of them with ſuch bravery of <hi>Reſolution,</hi> that he fought them two hours, and was ſo fortunate as to diſable one of them, which the reſt had enough to do to carry off; but by the way ſhe appeared to be on Fire, cauſed by ſome Fire-balls that had been ſhot into her. This Gentleman <hi>de Martel</hi> ſeems by many Circumſtances a moſt Gallant Man, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of his own Honour, and the Honour of his Nation, and Faithful to the utmoſt; ſo that when he had obſerved the Carriage of his own Admiral Count <hi>d' Eſtrees</hi> upon this
<pb facs="tcp:52683:9"/>occaſion, he after the Fight ſent the Prince an Account thereof in a particular Relation, it being as he ſaid, the ſame that he had ſent to his Maſter the King of <hi>France;</hi> wherein he taxed the Count, that he gave thoſe <hi>Zealan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> leave to paſs by the whole Squadron of the <hi>French</hi> with their diſabled Ship, to ſecure her and themſelves in making back to the reſt of their <hi>Zealand</hi> party: of which when <hi>de Martel</hi> challenged the Captains of his Diviſion for failing to relieve him, they ſaid they had Orders from Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>d' Eſtrees</hi> to regard none of his Motions, ſo that it ſeems the Count choſe rather to venture a point of Honour, then depart from his own private reſerve of mind. This Action being over, <hi>de Martel</hi> retired, and united again with the main Body of the <hi>French</hi> Squ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dron; where he afterwards durſt not be ſo forward any more, but ſtood as ſtill as the reſt of his Fellows: Of which more by and by.</p>
            <p>By this behaviour of <hi>d' Eſtrees</hi> there is Ground enoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to Collect, That <hi>de Ruyter</hi> and the <hi>Zealand Vice-Admirat</hi> were before-hand pretty Confident, that the <hi>French</hi> would not hurt them: which made the <hi>Zealander</hi> ſend only that ſmall party of Men of War, to fall upon <hi>de Martel</hi> for his forwardneſs; elſe there had been no reaſon he ſhould have preſumed ſo far to neglect the <hi>French,</hi> as to unite himſelf and all the reſt of his <hi>Zealanders</hi> with the Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of <hi>de Ruyter,</hi> to bring their whole Force upon his Highneſs.</p>
            <p>It was about 8. a Clock e're the Fight began, and before 9. there fell a Fogg, with a ſmall Rain, which continued untill nigh Noon; then it cleared up, and the Wind came to the South, which put the <hi>French,</hi> being a head, to Windward of the <hi>Dutch:</hi> And then the Battel being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, the whole burthen and brunt of <hi>de Ruyter</hi> and <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaert,</hi> (thoſe Men of War alſo that fought <hi>de Martel</hi> being <hi>United</hi>) fell again upon his Highneſs and Sir <hi>John Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> Diviſion, while the <hi>French,</hi> inſtead of Tacking and
<pb facs="tcp:52683:10"/>Engaging the Enemy (as was expected from them) ſtood away to the <hi>S. E.</hi> the Wind then at <hi>S. S. W.</hi> and ſtood full two Leagues away before they Tack'd again, adding this Complyment to the former, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> when they gave the eight <hi>Zealand</hi> Men of War free paſſage back from <hi>de Martel</hi> to their Fellows. Now as this gave great Encouragement to the Enemy, ſo it would have appell'd any Man leſs Couragious then the Prince to ſee himſelf thus deſerted. But beſides this, it was ſtrange that Sir <hi>Edward Spragg,</hi> contrary to Order, and to the ſolemn aſſurance that he gave his Highneſs in Perſon the day before, not to be from his ſide, ſhould make a ſeparate Fighting with <hi>Tromp</hi> ſo far Leeward of all the reſt. Nor was his Highneſſes Reer-Admiral Sir <hi>John Chichely</hi> with his Diviſion near, becauſe the Enemy had ſoon interpoſed between him and the Prince: ſo that betwixt twelve and one of the Clock, his Highneſs was wholly ſurrounded by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> being preſſed by <hi>de Ruyter</hi> and his Squadron on his Lee-quarter, an Admiral with two Flags more on his Weather-quarter, and the <hi>Zealand</hi> Squadron on his broad-ſide to Windward. Thus they imployed all their Forces, having deſigned to take no more notice of the <hi>French</hi> than the <hi>French</hi> did of them, or of his Highneſs; although they had continually in their Eye the <hi>Blew Flagg ſet upon the Mizon Peek,</hi> which was the Signal to fall on, Expreſly ſet down in the General Inſtructions for Fighting, which had been ſent before by his Highneſs to Count <hi>d' Eſtrees;</hi> which hath been atteſted alſo by <hi>Martel</hi> in his Relation, and that the Prince did give the Signal before mentioned, with all other ſigns that might incite <hi>d' Eſtrees</hi> to bear down to his Aſſiſtance, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a fair Wind for the purpoſe; but that inſtead of this, he kept the Wind, contenting himſelf to give his Ships more then common and half diſtance from the Enemy. And 'tis related further by <hi>de Martel,</hi> That himſelf ſaw very well how ſhameful this was; but being under Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand now, not to Attempt any thing without Order from
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52683:10"/>the Count; and beſides, not daring to truſt the Captains of his own party to follow him, who in the former Action this day had deſerted him, he ſhrugged up his Shoulders, and could do no more but forbid any ſhooting from his Ship: And he concludes his Relation with theſe words, <hi>That if the Count would have fallen in with the fair wind upon</hi> de Ruyter <hi>and</hi> Bankaert, <hi>at their firſt Engaging, who far exceeded the Prince in number of force, they muſt needs have been incloſed between his</hi> Highneſs <hi>and</hi> d' Eſtrees, <hi>and ſo there would have been an entire Defeat of the Enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, his Highneſs proſecuted the Fight on with an undanted mind, and ſo Anſwered them at all points, that he gave them enough of it, and ſo forced them to give way, that he ſoon got an opportunity to joyn with Sir <hi>John Chichely:</hi> which being done, about two of the Clock his Highneſs diſcovered Sir <hi>Edward Spragg</hi> with his <hi>Blew Squadron</hi> at a great diſtance, about 3. Leagues to Lee-ward bearing <hi>N. N. E,</hi> and not knowing what condition that Squadron was in, and not hearing the Guns well plyed, he made all the Sayl he could towards them, to unite and relieve them, if he ſhould find occaſion requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it.</p>
            <p>No ſooner had <hi>de Ruyter</hi> perceived the deſign of the Prince, but he left Firing, and boar away alſo with his whole Fleet, to the relief of <hi>Tromp;</hi> ſo that both Fleets ran down ſide by ſide within Range of Cannon-ſhot; but without firing on either ſide; and as we were Sayling down we ſaw many of <hi>Spragg's</hi> Blew Squadron, which we judged had received ſome damage to Windward of his Body; and ſome of the <hi>Red</hi> likewiſe, to whom his Highneſs fired <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Gun, as a call to them to bear down to him: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding which they did not; but about 4. a Clock we were got nigh the <hi>Blew Squadron,</hi> where we found Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Spragg's</hi> Ship the <hi>Royal Prince</hi> wholly diſabled, her Main maſt, Mizon-maſt, and foretop-maſt ſhot away, and divers more Ships of his Squadron diſabled, the Vice-Admiral
<pb facs="tcp:52683:11"/>of the Blew laying to Windward of her, mending his Sayls and Rigging; the Earl of <hi>Oſſory,</hi> Reer-Admiral of the Blew, lay a ſtern of the <hi>Royal Prince,</hi> between her and the Enemy; bending of his new Sayles, and mending his Rigging, and two Frigats by him: whereupon, his <hi>Highneſs</hi> ſent two Frigats to take the <hi>Royal Prince</hi> in a Tow.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Tromps</hi> Squadron lay to the Eaſtward of them, ſome of them Diſabled alſo of their Top-maſts and Yards, part of his Squadron with his Vice-Admiral and Reer-Admiral ſtanding to the Eaſtward cloſe by a Wind with all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Sayl they could to gain it, and ſo they Tack't again upon the Blew; at which time we came near them, being about 4. a Clock: Then <hi>de Ruyter</hi> fired a Gun, upon which <hi>Tromp</hi> Tackt, with deſign to make themſelves Maſters of our Lame Ships, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Royal Prince</hi> and others; the <hi>Royal Prince</hi> being bravely defended by Sir <hi>John Kempthorn,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Oſsory,</hi> and Aſſiſted by ſome of the ſame Squadron. This made us lay by for Sir <hi>John Kempthorn,</hi> to get our Fleet in order to Attack the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my again, and then his Highneſs put out the <hi>Blew Flagg upon the Mizon-Peek,</hi> which is the uſual Signal to bring all the Ships into the Generalls Wake or Grains, and ſent Ketches, Sloops and Boats, to Ships that were to windward, to Command them in: whereupon we bore up, and ſteered in between <hi>de Ruyter</hi> and our Lame Ships, and fired a Gun to ſome of our own Ships to Windward to bear down; but none came near to Aſſiſt his Highneſs but Sir <hi>John Kemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn</hi> and my Lord of <hi>Oſſory;</hi> ſo we have reaſon to believe, that except his Highneſs had comein ſo happily to the relief; the <hi>Blew Squadron</hi> had been totally loſt, ſince they were ſo Diſabled, that no more of them but thoſe two Flaggs only were in a condition to give him any Aſſiſtance in a further encountring with the Enemy.</p>
            <p>About 5. a Clock <hi>de Ruyter,</hi> with all his Flaggs and Fleet came ſide by ſide cloſe up with the Prince: ſo there began
<pb facs="tcp:52683:11"/>a very ſharp Engagement; his Highneſs had none beſides the Vice-Admiral and Reer-Admiral of the Blew to ſecond him, but Sir <hi>John Harman,</hi> Capt, <hi>Davis</hi> in the <hi>Triumph,</hi> Capt, <hi>Stout</hi> in the <hi>Warſpight;</hi> and his Highneſſes own Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Sir <hi>John Holmes</hi> in the <hi>Rupert,</hi> Capt. <hi>Legg</hi> in the <hi>Royal Katherine,</hi> Sir <hi>John Berry</hi> in the <hi>Reſolution,</hi> Sir <hi>John Earnley</hi> in the <hi>Henry,</hi> Sir <hi>Roger Strickl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd</hi> in the <hi>Mary,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Carter</hi> in the <hi>Crown,</hi> a 4th. Rate Ship; in all, not above 13, or 14. Ships: The Fight was very ſharp and cloſe; about 7. a Clock his Highneſs forced the Enemy into a very great diſorder, and then ſent two Fire-ſhips amongſt them; which increaſed it; and if the <hi>French,</hi> who now again lay at a convenient diſtance to Windward, would have obeyed the Prince his Signal, and bore down upon the Enemy according to their Duty, we muſt needs have Routed them, and Torn them to Pieces. It was the plaineſt and greateſt opportunity that ever was loſt at Sea. The Fight continued till the day was nigh ſpent, and the Sun juſt ſetting; at which time his Highneſs ſeeing my Lord of <hi>Oſſory</hi> and Sir <hi>John Kempthorn</hi> both in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure Diſabled, and none elſe likely to be Aſſiſting to make a through end of the Buſineſs, it was high time to carry off our diſabled Ships; to which purpoſe he edged off to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them with an eaſie Sayl, and the <hi>Dutch</hi> laid their heads to the Eaſtward: ſo the Battel ended.</p>
            <p>When the Night had parted us and the Enemy, and no more was to be done, came a Meſſenger from Count <hi>d' Eſtrees</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Admiral, to demand Orders, and to know what was meant by the <hi>Blew Flagg upon the Mizon-Peek,</hi> though all the Engliſh knew, and ſo did his own Vice-Admiral acknowledge, and the Inſtructions for Fighting which the Prince had ſent him, and others of the <hi>French</hi> Captains can tell, and all the World, that he had as much Reaſon to know it, and more Eminently, than any of themſelves; however, it was cunningly done of Count <hi>d' Eſtrees,</hi> by a ſpecial Meſſage to compleat the
<pb facs="tcp:52683:12"/>whole affair thus with a perfect Mockery, after the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> had ſtood off to their own Coaſt.</p>
            <p>As to the Damage on either ſide, great Execution was done upon the Tackle and Rigging by both Parties, and divers Ships diſabled; <hi>Tromp</hi> ſhifted his Ship on that Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count once, and Sir <hi>Edward Spragg</hi> twice; ſo that when the <hi>Royal Prince</hi> was diſabled, he went and ſet up his Flag in the <hi>St. George;</hi> which becoming diſabled alſo, he was fain to take Boat to go on Board the <hi>Royal Charles,</hi> and had not Rowed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ten Boats length, but a Bullet came and broke his Boat: They made back again as faſt as they could, but before they could get within throw of the Ropes, the Boat ſunk, and Sir <hi>Edward Spragg</hi> was drowned, though when he was taken up his Head and Shoulders were found above Water, his Arms having taken ſo dead a hold of ſome part of the Boat, that they could not diſ-engage him from it. Neither we nor the <hi>French</hi> loſt one Ship of War; only the <hi>Henrietta</hi> Yatch was ſunk by the ſide of my Lord of <hi>Oſſory.</hi> Of the ſlain we are to reckon Captain <hi>Leneve,</hi> Captain <hi>Merryweather</hi> of the Duke of <hi>Buckinghams</hi> Regiment being Foot-Officers, and Mr. <hi>May</hi> a Volunteer. Of Sea-Commanders Sir <hi>William Reeves</hi> (a perſon of great bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, one that from his youth had been Educated by his Highneſs, and who had conſtantly attended him with high Courage, and Fidelity in all Fortunes by Sea and Land; ſo that he arrived to the skill, and made good the Character of a Gallant Commander) and Captain <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>war!</hi> (a Gallant old Sea man) both dyed of their wounds, which were all of note that we hear of. In his Highneſs's own Ship were ſixty men ſlain and dangerouſly wounded.</p>
            <p>What the Enemy loſt was hard to determine; but two of their great Ships of 70. and 60. Guns were loſt, in our ſight, the one ſunk by Sir <hi>John Kempthorne.</hi> Two of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Flag-Officers with ſeveral Captains were ſlain; and of Common Sea-men a very conſiderable number.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:52683:12"/>
            <p>Now, having run over all the particulars of this Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers Action, let us pauſe a little, and conſider the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick behaviour of this Excellent Prince; how Gloriouſly he acquitted himſelf in all the parts of a great General, and whether it were poſſible for any Man, under ſuch Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, to do more then he hath done? In the midſt of ſo many Intrigues of Oppoſition here at home, ſo many delays of his Commiſſion, ſo few Powers contained in it, ſuch ſcantly number of Sea-men, ſo little aſſurance of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Chief Commanders, ſuch failure of Proviſions, ſuch want of Ammunition and all other Neceſſaries, ſuch deceit of Navy-Officers, ſuch non-obſervance of Orders at Sea amongſt his own <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſo manifeſt defections of the <hi>French,</hi> not to be Staggered in his Reſolutions, nor to be put out of all Patience and Prudence in Action, nor to abate of his Affection and Zeal for the Honour and Service of His Majeſty, the ſafeguard and Intereſt of Religion and the Kingdom, in a ſeaſon when ſo many Popiſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors plaid a Game under board, and above too, will be an everlaſting Argument of his Highneſſes Valour and Renown; and muſt needs be a ſtrong Obligation upon the King, the Parliament, and People of <hi>England;</hi> who are now left to judge, whether it was not a wonderful good Providence of God, and one of the moſt memorable pieces of Service ever done at Sea, to ſurmount all thoſe difficulties, and even Envy it ſelf; and after all, to bring home the Fleet <hi>Royal</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> without the loſs of one Man of War, to her own Shore in Safety, in deſpight of all Enemies that deſigned otherwiſe by Sea and Land.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tantum potuit unius viri virtus, &amp; fortuna.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
